Guide to the J. Walter Thompson Company. Bill Sharfman papers, 1958-2010 and undated RL.11325
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
J. Walter Thompson Company. Bill Sharfman papers
1958-2010 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
J. Walter Thompson Company
RL.11325
9.0 Linear Feet
Founded in 1864, the J. Walter Thompson Company (JWT) is one of the oldest and largest enduring advertising agencies in the United States. It is headquartered in New York. Bill Sharfman was an executive who worked in strategic planning for JWT USA in New York as well as for the JWT subsidiary Brouillard Communications before opening his own agency, Sharfman & Co. The J. Walter Thompson Company Bill Sharfman papers include correspondence, speeches, research and policy reports and other printed materials, as well as audiovisual materials (video- and audio cassettes). Companies represented include Brouillard Communications, Chevron (Standard Oil of California), Ernst & Young (PACE Awards), GM, Goodyear, Harvard Business School, Kodak, Olivetti, Renault, Rockefeller Center, St. Ivel (Dairy Crest), Tayto (Golden Wonder), Televisión Nacional de Chile, and McNeil (Tylenol). Acquired as part of the John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History.
Arrangement
Arranged into the following series: General Files; Brouillard Communications; J. Walter Thompson; Sharfman & Co.; Speeches; Academic Career; Print Materials; Automotive Industry; Audiovisual Materials.
Biographical / Historical
Founded in 1864, the J. Walter Thompson Company (JWT) is one of the oldest and largest enduring advertising agencies in the United States. It is headquartered in New York. William L. (Bill) Sharfman was an executive who worked in strategic planning for JWT USA in New York as well as for the JWT subsidiary Brouillard Communications before opening the Sharfman & Co. agency.
William L. Sharfman was born in 1942. Sharfman graduated from the University of Michigan (BA, 1964) and Columbia University (MA, 1965; PhD, 1969). Sharfman taught at Columbia (Preceptor and Lecturer, 1966-1970) and Idaho State University (Dept. of English, 1970-1972). Sharfman worked at Time Sharing Information Services (President, 1972-1973); Metragraphic Systems (Vice-President, 1973-1976); J. Walter Thompson (Research and Planning, 1976-1978; Senior Vice-President, Strategic Planning, 1982-1985) and Brouillard Communications (Planning Director, 1978-1982). Sharfman opened the Sharfman & Co. agency in 1985.
Access Restrictions
Access note. Collection contains audiovisual/photographic formats that may need to be reformatted before use. Contact Research Services for access.
Provenance
The J. Walter Thompson Company. Bill Sharfman papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2016-2017.
Related Materials
Related materials may be found in the following Hartman Center collections: J. Walter Thompson Company Account Files; J. Walter Thompson Company Information Center records; J. Walter Thompson Company London Office records; Thomas Garbett papers.
Collection Overview
The J. Walter Thompson Company Bill Sharfman papers include correspondence, speeches, research and policy reports and other printed materials, as well as audiovisual materials (video- and audio cassettes). Companies represented include Brouillard Communications, Chevron (Standard Oil of California), Ernst & Young (PACE Awards), GM, Goodyear, Harvard Business School, Kodak, Olivetti, Renault, Rockefeller Center, St. Ivel (Dairy Crest), Tayto (Golden Wonder), Televisión Nacional de Chile, and McNeil (Tylenol). Acquired as part of the John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History.
Advertising; Advertising -- United States -- History; Advertising -- Great Britain -- History; Advertising agencies -- Chile; Advertising executives -- Chile; Advertising agencies -- Netherlands; Advertising agencies -- United States; Advertising agencies -- Great Britain; Advertising executives -- Great Britain; Advertising executives -- United States; Publicity -- History -- 20th century; Public relations; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History; Eastman Kodak Company; Chevron Corporation; Goodyear Tire and Rubber Company; Standard Oil Company; J. Walter Thompson Company. Brouillard Communications; Brouillard Communications, Inc.
- Brouillard Communications, 1978-1986 and undated; 1
  - Account planning outline, 1980-1981; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Clients in the News, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Communications audit guide, undated (Box 1)
  - Harvard Business School communications audit, 1981-1982; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Question area guides, 1978-1986 (Box 1)
  - Television Nacional de Chile communications audit, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Winning: Study of Corporate Reputations and Rewards, 1986 (Box 1)
- J. Walter Thompson Company, 1978-1996 and undated; 2
  - Action plan for marketing Rockefeller Center, 1983, 1996; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Allstate Savings communications audit presentation, 1983 (Box 2)
  - American Institute of Architects, 1982 (Box 2)
  - Amsterdam Office--Development of a Corporate Identity, 1980 (Box 2)
  - Chevron communications audit, 1979 (Box 2)
  - Communications audit guide, undated (Box 2)
  - Company Advertising: What It Is and How It Can Help, 1979 (Box 2)
  - Discussion about the concept of effective exposure and the criteria for developing a position, 1978 (Box 2)
  - Goodyear--Summary and conclusion of management survey of corporate advertising, 1978 (Box 2)
  - Guidelines for the use and selection of celebrities in advertising, 1978 (Box 2)
  - In Defense of the Press (Burt Manning), 1982 (Box 2)
  - London Office--Assessment of account planning, 1984 (Box 2)
  - London Office--Fulfilling the Potential of St. Ivel Gold, 1984 (Box 2)
  - London Office--Golden Wonder: A Potted Success Story, 1984 (Box 2)
  - London Office--St. Ivel market modeling, 1983 (Box 2)
  - New York credentials, 1982 (Box 3)
  - New York telephone directory, 1986 (Box 3)
  - Olivetti communications audit, 1979 (Box 3)
  - Oral History Project, 1989 (Box 3)
  - Product naming process, 1978 (Box 3)
  - Standard Oil of California communications audit, 1979; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - The New York Thompson, November 1981 (Box 3)
  - Trintex (videotex service) communications audit, 1986; 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Tylenol strategy (after product tampering incident), 1982 (Box 3)
- Sharfman & Co., 1986-1989 and undated; 3
  - Chemical Bank Credit Card Anti-Attrition Project, 1988 (Box 4)
  - Communications Audits and Management (UK), undated; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - GGK Communications Audit, 1986 (Box 4)
  - GGK Communications Audit - Correspondence, 1986 (Box 4)
  - Newton Lao Leonard & Locke (NY), undated (Box 4)
  - Sandoz Branding Communications Audit (1987), 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Sharfman & Co. Communications Audit, undated (Box 4)
  - Washington Mutual Positioning Audit, 1989 (Box 4)
- Speeches, 1982-1984 and undated; 4
  - Advertising Wars, 1984 (Box 4)
  - JWT Creative Philosophy: The Roots of Communication, 1983 (Box 4)
  - Names, Leadership and Teamwork, 1983 (Box 4)
  - National emergency executive briefing on product tampering, 1982 (Box 4)
  - Promoting Smart Driving Habits, undated (Box 4)
- General Files, 1958-approximately 2010 and undated; 5
  Scope and Contents
  Highlights of the General Files include: materials related to the School of Jazz/Music Inn in Lenox, MA in the late 1950s; an interview with Dr. W. Edwards Deming; and a White House Summit on Innovation in 1999.
  - Biographical information and resumes, 1982-approximately 2010 (Box 5)
  - Brookings Institution, 1990-1991 (Box 5)
    informational packet on the Brookings Institution
  - CEO's Mission or Vision Development Guide, 2002 (Box 5)
  - Clipping--Estamos de epoca de guerras publicitarias (Chile), approximately 1984 (Box 5)
  - Clippings, 1960-1990 (Box 5)
    Clippings from the Worcester Sunday Telegram, March 6, 1960; New York Times, July 26, 1990
  - Clippings Related to Sharfman's Promotion, 1982 (Box 5)
    Clippings included with letters sent to Sharfman from JWT and other ad agencies congratulating him on his promotion in 1982
  - Communications Audit Presentation, 1987 (Box 5)
  - Competitive strategies, undated (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1976-1999, bulk 1982-1984 (Box 5)
    Correspondence from before, during, after Sharfman's work in advertising. Bulk of correspondence relates to a promotion at JWT in 1982.
  - David E. Davis Commencement Speech (Michigan), 2004 (Box 5)
  - Deming - Interview with Sharfman, 1991 (Box 5)
  - Deming - Quality, Productivity, and Competitive Position Seminar, 1991; 2 folders (Box 5)
    Dr. W. Edwards Deming
  - Design Leadership Symposium, 1992 (Box 5)
  - Donaldson, Lufkin & Jenrette--What Makes Great Advertising? What Is the Role of Planning?, approximately 1991 (Box 5)
  - Ernst & Young - Lean Manufacturing Plant Performance Assessment, 2000 (Box 5)
  - Fluor Corp Question Guide, undated (Box 5)
  - Global Business Network - Future of Electronic Advertising, 1989 (Box 5)
  - Global Business Network - Publications, 1994 (Box 5)
    NetView Winter 1994/95, Wired article about Global Business Network, GBN Book Club 1994
  - Global Business Network - Values and the Corporation, 1994 (Box 5)
  - HEW - Human Response to Patterns of Urban Density, 1969 (Box 5)
  - Idaho - Publications/Writing, 1972-1973 (Box 5)
    Miscellaneous newsletter articles for Sun Valley, Idaho, and Time-Sharing Today, publication proofs for an article on Malamud in Rendezvous, and two undated pieces on essay mills and the interstate highway system
  - Kodak color paper advertising, 1978 (Box 5)
  - Kodak research, approximately 1978 (Box 5)
  - Life in the Fast Lane: Electronics, the Biggest, Fastest Game in Town, 1995 (Box 5)
    Presentation by Craig Barrett, Intel, at MIT, 1995
  - Metagraphic Systems, 1973-1976 (Box 5)
  - Philip Morris - Gateway - "A Friendly First Step", 1990-1991 (Box 5)
    Materials related to Philip Morris-sponsored adult literacy program in Philadelphia.
  - Philip Morris - Gateway - Paths to Adult Learning, 1990-1991; 4 folders (Box 5)
  - Philip Morris Gateway: The First Meeting, 1990-1991 (Box 5)
  - Philip Morris Gateway Project - Press Releases, 1990 (Box 5)
  - Photo, 1962 (Box 5)
    Action shot of an unidentified man riding a motorcycle
  - RDC Corporation, Oakland Urban Entertainment Center (MI), 1990s (Box 5)
  - Research on solar energy products, 1978 (Box 5)
  - Rockefeller Center Development Corporation, undated (Box 5)
  - Rockefeller Center, Correspondence, approximately 1993 (Box 5)
  - Rockefeller Center, Customer Service Report, 1992 (Box 5)
  - Rockefeller Center, Re-Engineering Tenant Support Engineering, 1995 (Box 5)
  - School of Jazz/Music Inn, 1958-1959; approximately 2000 (Box 5)
    Records from Sharfman's time at the School of Jazz in Lenox MA, as well as information about the documentary, Music Inn. Jazz musicians such as Ornette Coleman, Max Roach, Bill Evans, Don Cherry, and Jimmy Giuffre, among others, are mentioned.
  - Strategic Planning Workshops Notes, approximately 1980; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Strategy for the Future, 1979 (Box 5)
  - Strategy Workshop, 1976 (Box 5)
  - Summit on Innovation: Federal Policy for a New Millennium, 1999 (Box 5)
  - Sun Valley Creative Arts Center, 1974 (Box 5)
  - Sun Valley Summer School - Correspondence, 1971-1972 (Box 5)
  - Sun Valley Summer School - Enrollment, 1971-1972 (Box 5)
  - We've Merged. Big Deal., approximately 1980 (Box 5)
  - Wharton School - Creating and Implementing Quality in Organizations, 1991 (Box 5)
  - What company is/perceived to be, undated (Box 5)
  - Winning the Innovation Race (Preface and Acknowledgments), 2000 (Box 5)
    Copies of Preface and Acknowledgments from Lee Sage, Winning the Innovation Race.
- Academic Career, 1965-1973 and undated; 6
  The Academic series includes materials from Sharfman's career as an English professor, includingsuch as bibliographies, exams, assignments, lecture notes, and teaching evaluations.
  - "Inside and Outside Malamud" - Drafts, undated (Box 6)
  - "The City in Literature," Commentary, v. 51, #5, May 1971 (Box 6)
  - "Urban Monkeys" Article, undated (Box 6)
  - Assignment Sheets for Upper Division Courses, approximately 1970 (Box 6)
  - Bibliographies, undated (Box 6)
  - Columbia Placement, approximately 1969 (Box 6)
  - Exams & Assignments, undated (Box 6)
  - Idaho - Misc., 1970-1971 (Box 6)
    Includes correspondence with Con Edison
  - Idaho State - Teaching Evaluations, 1971-1972 (Box 6)
  - Job Letters/Recommendations, 1965-1973 (Box 6)
    Recommendations and job placement letters for Sharfman
  - Preparation for College English, Idaho State University, 1971 (Box 6)
  - Ralph Bates Book Contract, 1970-1973 (Box 6)
    Note from Sharfman: "Subject of my dissertation - project never completed"
  - Recommendation Letters, 1971-1972 (Box 6)
    Recommendation letters by Sharfman on behalf of other people
  - Teaching Notes, 1966-1972; 8 folders (Box 8)
    Sharfman's notes and syllabi for various courses in English at Idaho State and Columbia College; most undated. Course subjects include the city in modern literature, art and literature in the 19th century, and the novel. Explanatory note from Sharfman about his teaching method included in folder 1.
- Print Materials, 1986-2008 and undated; 7
  - "Corporate Image v. Corporate Mission", 1981 (Box 6)
  - "One Last Look at Oldsmobile", 2001 (Box 6)
    Brandweek, 2001
  - "A New Doctoral Program in English," College English, Dec. 1970 (Box 6)
  - "Corporate Image v. Corporate Mission", 1981 (Box 6)
  - "Some Remarks on Management in the Eleventh Hour," ADE Bulletin, Feb. 1977, 1976-1977 (Box 6)
    Bulletin also includes a feature on the state of the academic job market for English PhDs
  - "What Every Account Executive Should Know", 1989-1994; 5 booklets (Box 6)
  - Automobile Magazine, 1986-2000; 8 folders (Box 6)
    Various issues of Automobile magazine which include articles and interviews by Sharfman. Interviewees include Morley Safer (of 60 Minutes), Betsy Ancker-Johnson, Heinz Prechter, Steve Earle, Jerry Curry, and Emilio Anchisi. Articles include review of the Baedeker, and "Escape from Tokyo."
  - BBDO article feat. Sharfman, 1986 (Box 6)
    in Japanese
  - Design publications - miscellaneous, 1992 (Box 6)
    Design Management Journal, Winter 1992; A New Perspective on Design, Cheskin + Masten, 1992
  - Interviews - Padraig Flynn, 1993 (Box 6)
    interview with Padraig Flynn, EC Commissioner of Social Affairs
  - Interviews - William K. Reilly - Self Magazine, 1992 (Box 6)
    Interview with EPA Administrator, William K. Reilly
  - Las Vegas Life, 1999-2000; 4 folders (Box 6)
    Various issues of Las Vegas Life which include automotive reviews and commentary by Sharfman
  - Philip Morris - "In the Public Interest", 1988 (Box 6)
  - Porsche Panorama, 1997 (Box 6)
  - Promax and BDA Conference Program, 1993 (Box 6)
  - Published Articles - John White - Art Exhibition Review, 2008 (Box 6)
  - Published Articles/Op-Eds (Misc), approximately 1980 (Box 6)
  - Published articles/op-eds (misc.), approximately 1980 (Box 6)
  - Rockefeller Center, "Center" Magazine, 1993 (Box 6)
  - Scientist, Sept. 2006 (Box 6)
    Article on "Mercedes and the Boxfish"
  - Self - The New Diversity IV: Images of the Future - A Report on the American Woman, 1991 (Box 6)
- Automotive Industry, 1990-2004 and undated; 8
  The Automotive series documents the early years of the Ernst & Young/Automotive News PACE Awards for Innovation, for which Sharfman served as a judge for several years. The series also includes several presentations related to automotive innovation in the 1990s. The bulk of Sharfman's automobile reviews and related writing can be found in the Print Materials series.
  - 6th Annual World Traffic Safety Symposium, 1996 (Box 7)
    Includes conference program and 3 unidentified photographs
  - Automotive News Proofs, 2008 (Box 7)
  - Chrysler, 2002 (Box 7)
    Information on a 1933 Chrysler.
  - Driver Education, 1999-2001 (Box 7)
    Includes correspondence and two presentations on "Branded Driver Education in America" prepared for GM and AutoNation.
  - e-Car: Renault in North America, 1999 (Box 7)
    Presentation to Renault - framework for re-entering the US market
  - Ernst & Young - "The Car Company of the Future", 1993 (Box 7)
  - Ernst & Young - "The Concept Automotive Industry Project", approximately 2000 (Box 7)
  - Global Automotive Institute, approximately 2000; 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Interviews - Car Talk, undated (Box 7)
    Interview of Tom and Ray Magliozzi of "Car Talk"
  - Interviews - Schrempp, Jurgen (Chrysler), 1998 (Box 7)
  - Interviews - Shelby, Carroll, 2001 (Box 7)
    includes background research and notes for interview with maker of the Shelby Cobra
  - Miscellaneous articles, 1999-2004 (Box 7)
    short reviews of new models in Lifetime and Driving Forces magazine; including Toyota Avalon, Volvo S60, Cadillac CTS, and Sierra Denali.
  - PACE Automotive Innovation Forum, 1997 (Box 7)
  - PACE Automotive Innovation Forum, 1999 (Box 7)
  - PACE Automotive Innovation Forum, 2002 (Box 7)
  - PACE Awards - 1994-1995 - Judging Notes (Box 7)
  - PACE Awards - 1994-1995 - Site Visits (Box 7)
  - PACE Awards - 1996 - Site Visits (Box 7)
  - PACE Awards - 1997 - Judging Notes, 1996-1997 (Box 7)
  - PACE Awards - 1997 - Site Visit Summaries (Box 7)
  - PACE Awards - 1998 - Site Visits (Box 7)
  - PACE Awards - 2001 - Site Visits (Box 7)
  - PACE Awards - 4th Annual Automotive Innovation Forum, undated (Box 7)
  - PACE Awards - Applications, 1996-2001 (Box 7)
    Drafts of blank applications with markup, comments on innovation
  - PACE Awards - Findings Reports, 1995-1998 (Box 7)
  - PACE Awards - Previous PACE Finalists", approximately 2004 (Box 7)
    List of previous PACE finalists through 2004, undated
  - PACE Awards - Programs, 1998-2007 (Box 7)
  - PACE Race, 2000 (Box 7)
  - PACE, What We've Learned So Far - Correspondence, 1997; 3 folders (Box 7)
  - PACE, What We've Learned So Far - Drafts, 1997-1998 (Box 7)
  - VW-GM War Mediating, 1990-1993 (Box 7)
- Audiovisual Materials, 1981-2000 and undated; 9
  - Advertising Council Drug abuse and AIDS prevention, undated (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11325-VHS-001)
    "Ocean" :30; "Self-Realization" :60
  - Advertising Council Drunk driving prevention, undated (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11325-VHS-002)
    "Jack (Coffin)"; "Mike"; "Heavy Metal"; "Double Date"; "Barney". 2:30
  - Bell Helmets, 1996 (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11325-Umatic-001)
    Goodby, Silverstein. Bell Helmets "Reason/Siren Rev. 1" :30
  - Bob Hope Heart Research Institute, undated (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11325-Umatic-002)
    Interview with Dr. Vijay Kakkar. J. Walter Thompson. 40:39
  - Brouillard commercials, 1981 (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11325-Umatic-003)
    Brouillard Communications. Goodyear "Nuns" "Children"; Blue Cross/Blue Shield "Teenage Alcoholic"; Coors "Historical"; Textron "Bostich--Simple Idea"; Selchow & Righter "Suspense"; Irving Trust "Commuter"; Eaton "Vintage Truck"; CUNA "Farmer"; Goodyear "Lombardi"; Olivetti "Type Off".
  - Don't Drink and Drive, 1996 (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11325-VHS-003)
    Triangle, Whitfield House, London. "Glasses". NTSC copy
  - Dr. Vijay Kakkar, undated (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11325-Umatic-005)
    Interview with Dr. Vijay Kakkar. J. Walter Thompson. Edited Master
  - In Defense of the Press, 1983 (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11325-Umatic-006)
    J. Walter Thompson. In Defense of the Press; Master as used in Monte Carlo. 27:00
  - John Mack Carter/Good Housekeeping, 1982 (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11325-Umatic-007)
    John Mack Carter/Good Housekeeping interview. Master 54:00
  - Mercedes Benz, 1995 (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11325-Umatic-008)
    Lowe & Partners/SMS. Mercedes Benz spots: "Celebrity Intro"; "Cupids"; "Designers"; "Non Stop"; "Rhinos Black and White". 2:30
  - New York Times, 1982 (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11325-Umatic-009)
    A.O. Sulzberger. New York Times. Edited master. 32:00
  - Norman Cousins, 1983 (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11325-Umatic-004)
    Interview with Norman Cousins. J. Walter Thompson. 10:00
  - PACE 2000 (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11325-VHS-004)
    Ernst & Young (copyrighted). NTSC. SP. 5:55.
  - Phyllis Whitney/Glamour, 1982 (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11325-Umatic-010)
    Phyllis Whitney/Glamour interview. Master. 12:00
  - Richard McLaughlin/Readers Digest, 1982 (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11325-Umatic-011)
    Richard McLaughlin/Readers Digest interview. Master. 23:00
  - Savvy, 1982 (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11325-Umatic-012)
    Savvy Interview. Master. 26:00
  - Self, 1982 (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11325-Umatic-013)
    Lynne Berentson/Self interview. Master. 30:00
  - Unilever presentation, 1982 (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11325-Umatic-015)
    J. Walter Thompson. Unilever presentation "Interviews." 7:40
  - Unilever/In Defense of the Press, 1982 (Box AV1, Video-cassette RL11325-Umatic-014)
    J. Walter Thompson. Unilever/In Defense of the Press. 60:00
  - 3 voices, undated (Box AV2, Audio-cassette RL11325-CS-001)
    Roosevelt, Churchill, Nancy Zakreski
  - Cosmopolitan interview, 1982 (Box AV2, Video-cassette RL11325-Umatic-017)
    10-1-82. Helen Gurley Brown. Master. 22:00
  - Unilever presentation (editor interviews), 1982 (Box AV2, Video-cassette RL11325-Umatic-016)
    Editor interviews. Master. 4:00